<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Debian 12 on Atlas</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/tags/debian-12/</link><description>Recent content in Debian 12 on Atlas</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.javiercd.es/en/tags/debian-12/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Active Directory in Ubuntu</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/ad_ubuntu/ad_ubuntu/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/ad_ubuntu/ad_ubuntu/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this post, we will explore how to set up an Active Directory environment on an Ubuntu server using tools such as Kerberos and Samba. Active Directory is an integral Microsoft solution for identity management and access control in business networks. Through this guide, we will learn step by step how to implement a Ubuntu server as a domain controller, establish Kerberos-based authentication and configure directory services by using Samba.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Install and configure samba in Debian</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/samba_debian/samba_debian/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/samba_debian/samba_debian/</guid><description>&lt;p>Samba is a free and open source implementation of the Server Message Block (SMB) protocol, which is used to share files and printers on computer networks. The SMB protocol is a network protocol that allows Windows operating systems to communicate with other network devices, such as file servers, printers and other shared resources.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Samba facilitates interoperability between Windows systems and Unix / Linux-based operating systems by allowing Unix systems to share files and resources with Windows systems using the SMB / CIFS protocol. This means that a Samba server can act as a file server for Windows customers, allowing them to access and share files as if they were in a Windows environment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Linux task programming commands</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/comandos_linux/programacion_tareas/programacion_tareas/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/comandos_linux/programacion_tareas/programacion_tareas/</guid><description>&lt;p>The efficient management of programmed tasks is essential for system managers as it facilitates the automatic execution of routine processes. In this context, having a solid set of Linux commands to program and control tasks becomes a fundamental tool.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sleep-command">Sleep command&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The sleep command stops running in the terminal for a specified time interval before returning to the command line. You can indicate the time in seconds, minutes, hours or days. This command is found in the choreutils package.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Linux Process Management</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/comandos_linux/comandos_procesos/comandos_procesos/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/comandos_linux/comandos_procesos/comandos_procesos/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the Linux ecosystem, a process is the execution of a specific program that performs a particular task. Each process has its own unique identifier (PID) and is composed of a set of resources, such as memory and CPU, that allow it to operate independently.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the Linux universe, effective process management is a crucial ability to optimize performance and ensure system stability. This post will immerse you in the essential foundations of process management&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Migration of a file system</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/migraciones/migracion_sistema_de_ficheros/sistemas-de-ficheros/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/migraciones/migracion_sistema_de_ficheros/sistemas-de-ficheros/</guid><description>&lt;p>Sometimes, it is necessary to update the storage of our Debian system to meet the growing space needs and improve the organization of the disk. In this guide, we will explore the migration process from a single disk to one with greater capacity, as well as divide it into separate partitions for more efficient management.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This process will not only expand the available storage space, but also provide a more orderly structure to the system, facilitating tasks such as backup management, system performance and disk space management.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>