<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>WordPress on Atlas</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/tags/wordpress/</link><description>Recent content in WordPress on Atlas</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.javiercd.es/en/tags/wordpress/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>LAMP Stack Installation in Debian 12</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/lamp/lamp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/lamp/lamp/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="lamp-stack-installation-in-debian-12">LAMP Stack Installation in Debian 12&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you are using Debian 12, follow the steps below to install a full LAMP web server on Debian GNU/Linux 12 &amp;ldquo;Bookworm&amp;rdquo; (Stable). Note that Debian 12 includes PHP 8.2 in its repositories, which may differ from previous Debian versions.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="web-server-installation">Web Server Installation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The first component of a LAMP server is Apache, represented by the &amp;ldquo;A.&amp;rdquo; To install Apache, run the following commands:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>sudo apt install apache2
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>sudo systemctl enable apache2 &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span> sudo systemctl start apache2
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>With these commands, you will have installed and activated the Apache web server. You can verify its functionality by entering the server&amp;rsquo;s IP address in your favorite browser; it should display the default Apache home page.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>LEMP Stack Installation in Debian 12 with PHP 8</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/lemp/lemp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/lemp/lemp/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="lemp-stack-installation-in-debian-12-with-php-8">LEMP Stack Installation in Debian 12 with PHP 8&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In this guide, we will go through the steps to install a LEMP stack (Linux, Nginx, MariaDB, and PHP) on a Debian 12 server. The configuration includes PHP 8.2 as the main version. The LEMP stack is essential for hosting PHP-based websites and applications, such as WordPress or other dynamic applications. Follow the detailed steps below to configure your LEMP server with PHP 8.2.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>WordPress installation in Debian 12 with LAMP PHP-8</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/wordpress/instalacion_wordpress/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/wordpress/instalacion_wordpress/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="wordpress-installation-in-debian-12-with-lamp-php-8-battery">WordPress installation in Debian 12 with LAMP PHP-8 battery&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>WordPress is a very popular open source content management system (CMS) that is used to create and manage websites and blogs. It was first released in 2003 and has since won a wide user base and an active community of developers and designers.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="preparation">Preparation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Before we start installing WordPress, we will make clear in a list what the ecosystem of our server is so everything works out properly:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>WordPress installation in Debian 12 with PHP-8 LEMP battery</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/wordpress_lemp/instalacion_wordpress_lemp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/wordpress_lemp/instalacion_wordpress_lemp/</guid><description>&lt;p>#WordPress installation in Debian 12 with PHP-8 LEMP battery&lt;/p>
&lt;p>WordPress is a very popular open source content management system (CMS) that is used to create and manage websites and blogs. It was first released in 2003 and has since won a wide user base and an active community of developers and designers.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="previous-requirements">Previous requirements&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Linux server:&lt;/strong> You must have a server that runs Linux, the guide is designed for Debian 12.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>User with superuser permissions:&lt;/strong> You must have access to a user with sudo privileges on the server in order to perform the installation and configuration tasks.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Full Domain Name (FQDN):&lt;/strong> If you want to access your WordPress site through a custom domain, make sure you have a full domain name (FQDN) set up and pointed to the server.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Internet access:&lt;/strong> You need Internet access to download packages and make updates during the installation process.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Make sure you meet all these requirements before you start installing WordPress on your server.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>