<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>NFTABLES on Atlas</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/tags/nftables/</link><description>Recent content in NFTABLES on Atlas</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.javiercd.es/en/tags/nftables/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Implementation of a perimeter firewall with Nftables I</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_uno/cortafuegos_uno/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_uno/cortafuegos_uno/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In this post on a Debian machine scenario, we will apply rules with Nfables to match the traffic that goes into and out of our network, trying to imitate a scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[NOTE]
To deploy the stage to perform these exercises you will need to deploy the .yaml file you will find in the link to the next paragraph. This will be in charge of deploying 2 machines one that will make firewall and one that will simulate a client that will be connected to the first machine to simulate a local network.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Implementation of a perimeter firewall with Nftables II</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_dos/cortafuegos_dos/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_dos/cortafuegos_dos/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;On the stage created in the service module with the Odin (Router), Hela (DMZ), Loki and Thor (LAN) machines and using nftables, it sets up a perimeter firewall on the Odin machine so that the stage continues to function completely taking into account the following points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• The creation of different chains for each traffic flow (from LAN to the outside, from LAN to DMZ, etc.) will be valued.
• Default DROP policy for all chains.
• You can use the extensions that we create appropriate, but at least you should follow the connection when necessary.
• We must implement the firewall to work after a machine reboot.
• You must show proof of operation of all rules.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>