<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DEBIAN on Atlas</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/tags/debian/</link><description>Recent content in DEBIAN on Atlas</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.javiercd.es/en/tags/debian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Installation and Configuration of MariaDB in Debian 12</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/instalar_mariadb/instalar_mariadb/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/instalar_mariadb/instalar_mariadb/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="mariadb-installation-and-configuration-in-debian-12">MariaDB installation and configuration in Debian 12&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To install MariaDB in Debian 12, follow these steps:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>1.&lt;strong>Update the repositories and install the MariaDB package&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, update your system repositories and install MariaDB:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> javiercruces@jcruces:~$ sudo apt update
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> javiercruces@jcruces:~$ sudo apt install mariadb-server
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>2.&lt;strong>Enable and start the MariaDB service&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once installed, set MariaDB to automatically start the start and then start the service:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> javiercruces@jcruces:~$ sudo systemctl start mariadb
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> javiercruces@jcruces:~$ sudo systemctl enable mariadb
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>3.&lt;strong>Configure MariaDB&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Interconnection of database servers</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/interconexion_de_servidores/interconexion_servidores/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/interconexion_de_servidores/interconexion_servidores/</guid><description>&lt;p>This post addresses how to configure and manage connections between different databases, both homogeneous and heterogeneous, to facilitate interoperability between various database systems. Throughout the article, different connection scenarios are explored, starting with configurations between databases of the same type, such as Oracle to Oracle or PostgreSQL to PostgreSQL, and then moving towards heterogeneous connections between different technologies, such as Oracle to MySQL, PostgreSQL to Oracle, and vice versa. It also covers the steps needed to configure links, create users, and modify key configuration files, allowing remote consultations.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Oracle installation 19c under Debian 12</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/instalacion_oracle_19c_debian12/instalacion_oracle/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/instalacion_oracle_19c_debian12/instalacion_oracle/</guid><description>&lt;p>Installing Oracle 19c on Debian 12 may seem complicated, but don&amp;rsquo;t worry, I&amp;rsquo;m here to guide you in every step. In this post, I will explain to you in a simple way how to prepare your system and make the installation of Oracle 19c in Debian 12.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="update-the-repositories">Update the repositories&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The first thing is to update the repositories of our virtual machine and in case we don&amp;rsquo;t have any packages we update it:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>PostgreSQL installation in Debian 12</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/instalar_postgresql/instalar_postgresql/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/instalar_postgresql/instalar_postgresql/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this post, I will guide you through the process of installing PostgreSQL in Debian 12, creating a user with basic permissions, and how to create and consult a database.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>#1. PostgreSQL installation&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To install PostgreSQL in Debian 12, follow these steps:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Update the repositories and install PostgreSQL * *:&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>First, make sure your system is updated and install PostgreSQL:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>```bash
sudo apt update
sudo apt install postgresql
```
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Verifies that the service is in operation * *:&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>After installation, make sure that the PostgreSQL service is in operation:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Remote access configuration in MariaDB</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/acceso_remoto_mariadb/acceso_remoto_mariadb/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/acceso_remoto_mariadb/acceso_remoto_mariadb/</guid><description>&lt;p>To allow remote access to your MariaDB server, follow these steps:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Configure the MariaDB configuration file&lt;/strong>
First, edit the MariaDB configuration file to allow connections from specific IP addresses. Open the file &lt;code>/etc/mysql/mariadb.conf.d/50-server.cnf&lt;/code> with a text editor, for example, &lt;code>nano&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>sudo nano /etc/mysql/mariadb.conf.d/50-server.cnf
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Find the line that starts with &lt;code>bind-address&lt;/code> and change it to accept connections from any IP address. You can have him accept connections from all the PIs with:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Remote Access Configuration in Oracle</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/oracle_acceso_remoto/oracle_acceso_remoto/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/base_de_datos/oracle_acceso_remoto/oracle_acceso_remoto/</guid><description>&lt;p>To configure remote access in Oracle, it is essential to correctly adjust the network files located in &lt;code>$ORACLE_HOME/network/admin&lt;/code>. These files, such as &lt;code>listener.ora&lt;/code> and &lt;code>tnsnames.ora&lt;/code>, allow us to define how clients will connect to the database and which equipment will have access.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="remote-access-configuration">Remote Access Configuration&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The Oracle configuration with respect to the network is saved in the directory that we have defined as the Oracle home: &lt;code>$ORACLE_HOME/network/admin&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.javiercd.es/base_de_datos/oracle_acceso_remoto/img/Aspose.Words.55b57132-3c19-4447-864b-0b88f1173a10.029.png" alt="Oracle network directory">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Comparative between OpenVPN and Wireguard</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/comparativa_ovpn_wire/comparativa_ovpn_wire/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/comparativa_ovpn_wire/comparativa_ovpn_wire/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.javiercd.es/vpn/comparativa_ovpn_wire/img/Pastedimage20240114150833.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The goal of this post is to compare the different VPNs software most used by seeing which is faster, for which we will support in speed test using iperf3.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>[NOTE]
The comparative part of the posts in this section in which we mount each type of VPN.&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="speed-without-vpn">Speed without VPN&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m gonna start by comparing the speeds of these 2 systems, using iperf3. For this I have removed the cisco router as I had it configured with FastEthernet interfaces and changed it to a Linux router with GigabitEthernet interfaces.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Create certification authority (CA) and self-signed certificates in Linux</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/seguridad/https_autofirmado/https_autofirmado/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/seguridad/https_autofirmado/https_autofirmado/</guid><description>&lt;p>At first a student will establish a Certified Authority and sign a certificate for the other student&amp;rsquo;s page. We will then test it on the Apache and Nginx web servers.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="create-the-certifying-authority">Create the certifying authority&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Step 1: Creating directories and files&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first step will be to generate a directory in which you will locate your certification authority, in order to maintain an organization at all times. The directory name will be CA /. In turn, you have to generate several subdirectories within it:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Forensic computer</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/seguridad/forense/forense/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/seguridad/forense/forense/</guid><description>&lt;p>Forensics is the set of techniques that allows us to obtain as much information as possible after a computer incident or crime.
In this practice, you will perform the evidence-taking and analysis phase on one Linux machine and another Windows. We&amp;rsquo;ll assume we caught the criminal &amp;lsquo;in fraganti&amp;rsquo; and the machines were on. Optionally, you can perform an Android device analysis.
On each of the machines you must do a memory and a hard drive, taking the necessary measures to certify the chain of custody.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Implementation of a perimeter firewall with Fortinet I</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/fortinet_uno/fortinet_uno/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/fortinet_uno/fortinet_uno/</guid><description>&lt;p>Before you start the practice, the scenario you see in the practice is as similar as I can ride to the original practice. I have used version 7.0.9-1 of FortiGate, as the higher versions bring some restrictions. You can download the image from this [link](&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/&lt;/a> 1VGmeLN5inkWNNNUsIvq9ewGUzJLTLkiM).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.javiercd.es/cortafuegos/fortinet_uno/img/Pastedimage20240320223139.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="firewall-start-up">Firewall start-up&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>FortiGate devices are made with the IP 192.168.1.99 / 24, as I am from GNS3 do not need to connect to this interface with a device and change the configuration. Since I can do it from the console.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Implementation of a perimeter firewall with Fortinet II</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/fortinet_dos/fortinet_dos/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/fortinet_dos/fortinet_dos/</guid><description>&lt;p>Now let&amp;rsquo;s emulate firewall practice II, but on GNS3. To this end, I have transformed client 1 into Odin, and added Thor and Loki as virtual machines instead of containers on the LAN network. I have also created a new network called DMZ, in which will be the Hela machine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since I have transformed the previous scenario into this new one, we have some rules created earlier. Therefore, I will remove from the statement those that are already created, such as making SSH to Odin from port 2222, but with the service listening in the 22.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Implementation of a perimeter firewall with Nftables I</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_uno/cortafuegos_uno/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_uno/cortafuegos_uno/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this post on a Debian machine scenario, we will apply rules with Nfables to match the traffic that goes into and out of our network, trying to imitate a scenario.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>[NOTE]
To deploy the stage to perform these exercises you will need to deploy the .yaml file you will find in the link to the next paragraph. This will be in charge of deploying 2 machines one that will make firewall and one that will simulate a client that will be connected to the first machine to simulate a local network.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Implementation of a perimeter firewall with Nftables II</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_dos/cortafuegos_dos/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_dos/cortafuegos_dos/</guid><description>&lt;p>On the stage created in the service module with the Odin (Router), Hela (DMZ), Loki and Thor (LAN) machines and using nftables, it sets up a perimeter firewall on the Odin machine so that the stage continues to function completely taking into account the following points:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>• The creation of different chains for each traffic flow (from LAN to the outside, from LAN to DMZ, etc.) will be valued.
• Default DROP policy for all chains.
• You can use the extensions that we create appropriate, but at least you should follow the connection when necessary.
• We must implement the firewall to work after a machine reboot.
• You must show proof of operation of all rules.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Installation of android in GNS3 with KVM</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/redes/android_gns3/android/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/redes/android_gns3/android/</guid><description>&lt;p>To download the android image you can do it from this page &amp;ndash; &amp;gt; &lt;a href="https://www.fosshub.com/Android-x86.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.fosshub.com/Android-x86.html&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>wget https://www.fosshub.com/Android-x86.html?dwl&lt;span style="color:#f92672">=&lt;/span>android-x86_64-9.0-r2.iso
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Create a KVM machine as if it were a Debian, I&amp;rsquo;ve given it 2GB of RAM and 2 Cores:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.javiercd.es/redes/android_gns3/img/Pastedimage20240117194542.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In our case we can launch an automatic installation:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.javiercd.es/redes/android_gns3/img/Pastedimage20240117194647.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you have the machine installed, turn off the machine and we&amp;rsquo;ll import it in gns3. To do this we will take the KVM disk and import it into the directory where we have installed the GNS3 images, then property the copied disk to your user.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Remote access VPN with Ipsec StrongSwan</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/acceso_remoto_strongswang/strongswang/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/acceso_remoto_strongswang/strongswang/</guid><description>&lt;p>StrongSwan is a VPN (Virtual Private Network) implementation based on IPsec, open source, multiplatform, complete and widely used. It works on operating systems such as Linux, FreeBSD, OS X, Windows, Android and iOS. Mainly, it is a key exchange demon that supports Internet Key Exchange protocols (IKEv1 and IKEv2) to establish security associations (SA) between two pairs.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>[NOTE]
I will start from the VPN post remote access with OpenVPN, so you may refer to this during this article. If you want to have the same scenario go first to this.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Remote access VPN with OpenVPN and x509 certificates</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/acceso_remoto_openvpn/accesoremoto_openvpn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/acceso_remoto_openvpn/accesoremoto_openvpn/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>One of the two teams (which will act as a server) will be connected to two networks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the authentication of the extremes, digital certificates shall be used, which shall be generated using openssl and stored in the / etc / openvpn directory, together with the Diffie- Helman parameters and the certificate of the Certification Authority itself.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Network addresses 10.99.99.0 / 24 will be used for VPN virtual addresses. The address 10.99.99.1 shall be assigned to the VPN server.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The server and client configuration files will be created in the / etc / openvpn directory of each machine, and will be called servor.conf and cliente.conf respectively.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>After the establishment of the VPN, the client machine must be able to access a machine on the other network to which the server is connected.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="riding-the-stage">Riding the stage&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>To perform this exercise I have mounted the following scenario on GNS3:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>VPN site to site Wireguard</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/site_to_site_wireguard/site_to_site_wireguard/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/site_to_site_wireguard/site_to_site_wireguard/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.javiercd.es/vpn/site_to_site_wireguard/img/Pastedimage20240114150833.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>[!NOTE]
I will start from the VPN post remote access with Wireguard, so you may refer to this one during this article.&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="key-generation">Key generation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The first thing we will do is to install both the Wireguard package in both machines:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>root@servidor1:~# sudo apt update &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span> sudo apt install wireguard
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>debian@servidor2:~$ sudo apt update &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span> sudo apt install wireguard
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s generate the pairs of keys that will be used to encrypt the connection. We will need a key for the server and a couple of additional keys for each client.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>VPN site to site with OpenVPN and x509 certificates</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/site_to_site_openvpn/site_to_site_openvpn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/site_to_site_openvpn/site_to_site_openvpn/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="riding-the-stage">Riding the stage&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>To perform this exercise I have mounted the following scenario on GNS3:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.javiercd.es/vpn/site_to_site_wireguard/img/Pastedimage20240114150833.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="swan-router-configuration">Swan router configuration&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s give each interface the corresponding network configuration:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#Interfaz que nos dará internet&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1#configure terminal
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#interface fastEthernet 0/0&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#ip add dhcp&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#no shut&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#exit&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#Interfaz red Servidor 1&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#interface fastEthernet 1/0&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#ip add 90.0.0.1 255.255.255.0&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#no shut&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#exit&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#Interfaz red Servidor 2&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#interface fastEthernet 1/1&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#ip add 100.0.0.1 255.255.255.0&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#no shut&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#exit&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#Ruta por defecto para internet&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#ip route 0.0.0.0 0.0.0.0 192.168.122.1&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#Guarda la configuración&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1#write
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#Configuración de SNAT&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1#conf term
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#access-list 1 permit 90.0.0.0 0.0.0.255&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#access-list 1 permit 100.0.0.0 0.0.0.255&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e"># ip nat pool NAT-Pool 192.168.122.127 192.168.122.127 prefix-length 24&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#ip nat inside source list 1 pool NAT-Pool overload&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#interface FastEthernet0/0&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#ip nat outside&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#interface FastEthernet1/0&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#ip nat inside&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#interface FastEthernet1/1&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>R1&lt;span style="color:#f92672">(&lt;/span>config-if&lt;span style="color:#f92672">)&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">#ip nat inside&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Server Configuration 1&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>VPN Wireguard remote access</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/acceso_remoto_wireguard/acceso_remoto_wireguard/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/vpn/acceso_remoto_wireguard/acceso_remoto_wireguard/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.javiercd.es/vpn/acceso_remoto_wireguard/img/Pastedimage20240114150833.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First I will configure the server machine as a VPN remote access and server server as a VPN client. I will then set up a Windows and Android client.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first thing we will do is to install both the Wireguard package in both machines:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>root@servidor1:~# sudo apt update &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span> sudo apt install wireguard
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>debian@servidor2:~$ sudo apt update &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span> sudo apt install wireguard
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s generate the pairs of keys that will be used to encrypt the connection. We will need a key for the server and a couple of additional keys for each client.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>LAMP Stack Installation in Debian 12</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/lamp/lamp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/lamp/lamp/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="lamp-stack-installation-in-debian-12">LAMP Stack Installation in Debian 12&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you are using Debian 12, follow the steps below to install a full LAMP web server on Debian GNU/Linux 12 &amp;ldquo;Bookworm&amp;rdquo; (Stable). Note that Debian 12 includes PHP 8.2 in its repositories, which may differ from previous Debian versions.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="web-server-installation">Web Server Installation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The first component of a LAMP server is Apache, represented by the &amp;ldquo;A.&amp;rdquo; To install Apache, run the following commands:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>sudo apt install apache2
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>sudo systemctl enable apache2 &lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span> sudo systemctl start apache2
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>With these commands, you will have installed and activated the Apache web server. You can verify its functionality by entering the server&amp;rsquo;s IP address in your favorite browser; it should display the default Apache home page.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>LEMP Stack Installation in Debian 12 with PHP 8</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/lemp/lemp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/lemp/lemp/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="lemp-stack-installation-in-debian-12-with-php-8">LEMP Stack Installation in Debian 12 with PHP 8&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In this guide, we will go through the steps to install a LEMP stack (Linux, Nginx, MariaDB, and PHP) on a Debian 12 server. The configuration includes PHP 8.2 as the main version. The LEMP stack is essential for hosting PHP-based websites and applications, such as WordPress or other dynamic applications. Follow the detailed steps below to configure your LEMP server with PHP 8.2.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>WordPress installation in Debian 12 with LAMP PHP-8</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/wordpress/instalacion_wordpress/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/wordpress/instalacion_wordpress/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="wordpress-installation-in-debian-12-with-lamp-php-8-battery">WordPress installation in Debian 12 with LAMP PHP-8 battery&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>WordPress is a very popular open source content management system (CMS) that is used to create and manage websites and blogs. It was first released in 2003 and has since won a wide user base and an active community of developers and designers.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="preparation">Preparation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Before we start installing WordPress, we will make clear in a list what the ecosystem of our server is so everything works out properly:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>WordPress installation in Debian 12 with PHP-8 LEMP battery</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/wordpress_lemp/instalacion_wordpress_lemp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/iaw/wordpress_lemp/instalacion_wordpress_lemp/</guid><description>&lt;p>#WordPress installation in Debian 12 with PHP-8 LEMP battery&lt;/p>
&lt;p>WordPress is a very popular open source content management system (CMS) that is used to create and manage websites and blogs. It was first released in 2003 and has since won a wide user base and an active community of developers and designers.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="previous-requirements">Previous requirements&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Linux server:&lt;/strong> You must have a server that runs Linux, the guide is designed for Debian 12.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>User with superuser permissions:&lt;/strong> You must have access to a user with sudo privileges on the server in order to perform the installation and configuration tasks.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Full Domain Name (FQDN):&lt;/strong> If you want to access your WordPress site through a custom domain, make sure you have a full domain name (FQDN) set up and pointed to the server.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Internet access:&lt;/strong> You need Internet access to download packages and make updates during the installation process.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Make sure you meet all these requirements before you start installing WordPress on your server.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Centralized collection of system log, using journald</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/recoleccion_logs_journald/recoleccion_logs_journald/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/recoleccion_logs_journald/recoleccion_logs_journald/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="step-1-install-system--journal-remote">Step 1 Install system -journal-remote&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In our environment, the first step will be to install the system-journal- remote package, which will allow us to access these machines remotely. To carry out the installation on our stage machines, we will use the apt package manager in Odin, which runs Debian 12. We will also install the same package in Thor and Loki, which are containers housed within Odin. As for Hela, a Rocky operating system, it will require the use of dnf for installation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Disposal of systemd</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/migraciones/eliminacion_systemd/eliminacion_systemd/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/sistemas/migraciones/eliminacion_systemd/eliminacion_systemd/</guid><description>&lt;p>Systemd and System V (SysV) are two start-up systems used in Linux distributions to manage system and service boot. System V (SysV) is a traditional start-up system that uses shell scripts stored at different running levels (runlevels) to start and stop services sequentially. It was widely used in many Unix and Linux distributions for decades. On the other hand, Systemd is a more modern and advanced start-up system that replaces SysV. Incorporated to improve system start speed and efficiency, systemd uses a unit-based approach and depends on paralleling to start services simultaneously. It also includes additional features such as service management, sockets, timers, and dependencies, making it a more robust and flexible option compared to SysV.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>