<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Drivers on Atlas</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/drivers/</link><description>Recent content in Drivers on Atlas</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/drivers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Installing NVIDIA Drivers on Debian 13</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/drivers/nvidia_driver/instalacion-controladores-nvidia-debian-13/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/drivers/nvidia_driver/instalacion-controladores-nvidia-debian-13/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The installation of NVIDIA drivers in the Linux universe has traditionally been a challenge, especially in distributions like Debian, where free software policies often complicate the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will explain a simple way to install NVIDIA drivers using the official Debian 13 (Trixie) repositories. In addition, at the end of the article, you will learn how to install a key tool called Nvidia Optimus, which gives you the ability to choose which graphics card your system will use.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Choose Which GPU to Use on My Laptop with Linux</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/drivers/nvidia_optimus/nvidia_optimus/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/drivers/nvidia_optimus/nvidia_optimus/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you have a Linux laptop with an NVIDIA GPU, you may have noticed that the video ports are not working properly after installing the graphics drivers. If this sounds familiar, don&amp;rsquo;t worry I’ve got you covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been investigating and found a tool that can save you several headaches. It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;strong&gt;EnvyControl&lt;/strong&gt;, a command-line utility (CLI) that allows you to easily choose which graphics card you want to use on your computer. This is especially useful if your laptop has a hybrid graphics configuration, such as Intel + NVIDIA or AMD + NVIDIA.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Installation of NVIDIA Controllers in Debian 12</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/drivers/nvidia_driver/instalacion-controladores-nvidia-debian-12/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/drivers/nvidia_driver/instalacion-controladores-nvidia-debian-12/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The installation of NVIDIA drivers in the Linux universe has traditionally been a challenge, especially in distributions such as Debian, where free software policies often complicate the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explain a simple way to install NVIDIA drivers using the official Debian repositories. In addition, at the end of the article, you will learn to install a key tool called Nvidia Optimus, which will provide you with the ability to select which graphics card you will use.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>