<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>FIREWALL on Atlas</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/tags/firewall/</link><description>Recent content in FIREWALL on Atlas</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.javiercd.es/en/tags/firewall/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Fortinet CLI</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/fortinet_cli/fortinet_cli/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/fortinet_cli/fortinet_cli/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="equivalence-from-gui-to-cli"&gt;Equivalence from GUI to CLI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, I started the practice using the command line (CLI), however, I found it more comfortable to do it from the graphic interface. Therefore, I decided to establish an equivalence between the different actions I have carried out during practice and to compare them with their counterpart in the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[NOTE]
In this post I do a small summary of the equivalencies between the GUI and the CLI of Fortinet that I have used in the 2 Fortinet firewall posts.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Implementation of a perimeter firewall with Fortinet I</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/fortinet_uno/fortinet_uno/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/fortinet_uno/fortinet_uno/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Before you start the practice, the scenario you see in the practice is as similar as I can ride to the original practice. I have used version 7.0.9-1 of FortiGate, as the higher versions bring some restrictions. You can download the image from this [link](&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/&lt;/a&gt; 1VGmeLN5inkWNNNUsIvq9ewGUzJLTLkiM).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.javiercd.es/cortafuegos/fortinet_uno/img/Pastedimage20240320223139.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="firewall-start-up"&gt;Firewall start-up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FortiGate devices are made with the IP 192.168.1.99 / 24, as I am from GNS3 do not need to connect to this interface with a device and change the configuration. Since I can do it from the console.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Implementation of a perimeter firewall with Fortinet II</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/fortinet_dos/fortinet_dos/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/fortinet_dos/fortinet_dos/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s emulate firewall practice II, but on GNS3. To this end, I have transformed client 1 into Odin, and added Thor and Loki as virtual machines instead of containers on the LAN network. I have also created a new network called DMZ, in which will be the Hela machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I have transformed the previous scenario into this new one, we have some rules created earlier. Therefore, I will remove from the statement those that are already created, such as making SSH to Odin from port 2222, but with the service listening in the 22.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Implementation of a perimeter firewall with Nftables I</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_uno/cortafuegos_uno/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_uno/cortafuegos_uno/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In this post on a Debian machine scenario, we will apply rules with Nfables to match the traffic that goes into and out of our network, trying to imitate a scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[NOTE]
To deploy the stage to perform these exercises you will need to deploy the .yaml file you will find in the link to the next paragraph. This will be in charge of deploying 2 machines one that will make firewall and one that will simulate a client that will be connected to the first machine to simulate a local network.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Implementation of a perimeter firewall with Nftables II</title><link>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_dos/cortafuegos_dos/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.javiercd.es/en/posts/cortafuegos/nftables_dos/cortafuegos_dos/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;On the stage created in the service module with the Odin (Router), Hela (DMZ), Loki and Thor (LAN) machines and using nftables, it sets up a perimeter firewall on the Odin machine so that the stage continues to function completely taking into account the following points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• The creation of different chains for each traffic flow (from LAN to the outside, from LAN to DMZ, etc.) will be valued.
• Default DROP policy for all chains.
• You can use the extensions that we create appropriate, but at least you should follow the connection when necessary.
• We must implement the firewall to work after a machine reboot.
• You must show proof of operation of all rules.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>